Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1104, Education Division; Records apap132
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Communications Workers of America Education Division Local 1104 Records
1969-2001 (bulk 1983-1999)
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Communications Workers of America. Local 1104 (Albany, N.Y.)
apap132
17.0 cubic ft.
The Education Division of Communication Workers of America, Local 1104 represents "employees eligible for union membership who are employed as: graduate students holding State-funded positions as Graduate Assistants or Teaching Assistants employed by the State University of New York." The collection includes news clippings, contracts, photographs, administrative records, as well as ephemera such as t-shirts, buttons, hats, and cup holders.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of the membership series. Researchers seeking access to Series #8 should contact the head of archives.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department Special Collections and Archives, by the Graduate Student Employees Union, CWA Local 1104.
Organizational Sketch
Beginning in the 1970s, graduate, teaching, and research assistants in the various schools of the State University of New York (SUNY) decided it would be beneficial to form a union for graduate student employees. Though they were students, they were also employed as assistants in a variety of capacities at their respective SUNY schools and wanted the right to bargain with the state of New York for fair employment conditions. [1] The movement began at SUNY Buffalo in 1975 and showed great promise based on the number of signatures gathered from graduate assistants up until 1977. [2] However, the movement suffered a temporary setback over issues regarding New York States Taylor Law, which forbids public employees to strike in order to preserve harmonious and cooperative relationships between government and its employees; it is also intended to protect the best interests of the public by making sure that government operations function smoothly and without interruption. [3] The law specifically recognizes public employees right to organize, utilize grievance procedures, and obtain the aid of a relations board to help them resolve differences with employers provided the employees are part of a legally recognized union. SUNY Buffalos early attempts to unionize were unsuccessful because although the organizers signed affidavits that they would uphold the Taylor Law, they had been part of two strikes prior to that time. As a result, the SUNY Buffalo administration decided not to authorize the Graduate Student Employees Union (GSEU).[4]
Organizing attempts began again in earnest in the early 1980s. Statewide organization became a priority when the Public Employee Relations Board (PERB) explained that such action was necessary for the GSEU to gain legal recognition. [5] Therefore, the largest of the SUNY campusesthe four university centers of Albany, Binghamton, Buffalo, and Stony Brook became the hubs of activity for union organizers. Initially, the students did not wish to be affiliated with larger unions like United University Professions, wary of giving up any independence. [6] However, after working to swell theirnumbers for several years, members eventually voted in 1984 to associate with the Communications Workers of America (CWA) since such an alliance would greatly strengthen the GSEUs bargaining power. [7]
Within months of coming under the wing of the CWA, the students decided to petition for a certification election that would allow graduate student employees to vote for or against unionization. After deliberating over the matter for two years, PERB decided in 1986 that the GSEU did not have the authority to vote on that issue. [8] PERBs reluctance to grant legal recognition to the GSEU was due in large part to their doubt about graduate students status as state employees; they viewed the organizers as students first and employees second, which meant that PERB questioned the organizers right to bargain in the first place. [9]
PERB ultimately decided to allow the graduate student employees to vote on unionization in 1991, but only for teaching and graduate assistants (TA and GA). Research assistants were not considered eligible as per PERBs existing rules, since they were (and still are) considered employees of the Research Foundation, not of SUNY. Believing that this was a step in the right direction, and that they could better advocate for the rights of research assistants if graduate and teaching assistants were legally recognized, the students went ahead and voted 6 to 1 to unionize. March 1994 brought the union its first contract after a year of negotiation, followed by two pay raises, creation of grievance procedures, and a health-care plan for student assistants, their spouses, and their dependents. [10] Rights such as grievance procedures did not come immediately, however, and the GSEU had to negotiate new contracts more than once before achieving some of the union benefits it wanted.
Completely student-run, the GSEU has a statewide executive committee that oversees union activity around New York. The elected officers take charge of procedures like policy planning and collective bargaining, but they are helped by elected officers of the steering committees at the SUNY schools, particularly the four university centers. Stewards on each campus are the eyes and ears of the steering committees and act as liaisons between the student body and steering committees. Members can be full or associate, depending on whether they are graduate/teaching assistants or not. The constitution, by-laws, and other policies of the GSEU are the products of the students themselves and have been amended as necessary over the years.[11]
In the winter of 2001, the members of GSEU whose division had previously been recognized as Local 1188merged with CWA Local 1112 (Telephone Traffic Union Upstate Workers) and CWA Local 1104 (Telecommunications) in order to gain more bargaining power. All three entities would then be known as CWA Local 1104, with all the bargaining power that such a union entails, but without having to give up the administrative structures and authorities set forth by the groups original charters. Original Local 1104 members became known as the Telecommunications Division, Local 1112 members became known as the Operator Services Division, and the old 1188 members became the Education Division. The organization of each division remained the same for three years, after which the CWA Local 1104 Executive Board could vote to make changes if necessary.[12]
As of spring 2010, the Graduate Student Employees Union was still active around the SUNY campuses, encouraging members to speak out on issues regarding TA and GA rights, and continuing to petition the governor and his colleagues on topics like tuition increases and fair wages. Research assistants, particularly at SUNY Stony Brook, have kept up their effortsto be recognized as official union members. In April 2010 the they brought their issues to New York State Attorney General Andrew Cuomo and United States Senator Kirsten Gillibrand in the hope of garnering support for a union contract, a victory they hope will be forthcoming.[13]
For more information on unions within the Communications Workers of America, refer to the finding aid for CWA Local 1104,Operators Division, which chronicles the union history of the New York Telephone (later AT&T) telephone operators.
The information provided above was gleaned from the following sources:
1. GSEU: An Organizing Guide, Series #1 Founding Papers
2. PERB. (14 November 2009). The Taylor Law: Public Employees Fair Employment Act. NYS Public Employee Relations Board. Retrieved 2 April 2010 from http://www.perb.state.ny.us/stat.asp#pol
3. GSEU: An Organizing Guide, Series #1 Founding Papers
4. 1995-1996 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
5. GSEU: An Organizing Guide, Series #1 Founding Papers
6. 1996-1997 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
7. 1995-1996 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
8. GSEU battling to bolster its membership, get recognition from the UB Reporter, 3 Feb. 1983, 14 (16).
9. 1995-1996 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
10. 1996-1997 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
11. 1995-1996 GSEU Stewards Manual, Series #2 Statewide Executive Division
12. Retrieved 31 March 2010 from http://www.gseurankandfile.org/fusion.html
13. Stony Brook RA Union. RA Union Meets NYS Attorney General Andrew Cuomo. Retrieved 3 May 2010 from http://sbraunion.org/
Scope and Contents
The collection arrived at the archives without a set order to the records, so the archivist imposed an arrangementon the records as they were processed. Many of the records reflect the activities of the GSEU statewide executive committee, which oversees the functions of the various branches of the union around New York State. Those records comprise a series of their own and mainly consist of administrative files such as correspondence, meeting minutes, activity planning, elections, and instructional information on how to organize. The executive committee held their meetings around the state, so material from them could appear on paper with letterheads from any of the center schools.
Each of the SUNY center schools makes up its own subseries under the heading of "Administrative Files. These subseries mirror some of the content from the statewide executive files, mainly correspondence and meeting minutes. There are also files dealing with day-to-day matters like mailing lists and local campus activities. The material from SUNY Buffalo by far outnumbers the material from Albany, Binghamton, and Stony Brook, which is likely because the GSEU movement was born in Buffalo. Therefore, the papers originating from that school are almost as numerous as those of the statewide executive committee.
This collection also contains papers documenting the founding of the GSEU: various financial materials (though not very many, considering that the bulk of the collection spans about seventeen years); publications from the SUNY campuses, especially from the unions themselves; and many subject files covering topics that were not deemed strictly administrative or applied to more than one location (and therefore were not filed under a specific school). Topics include issues with Univera Healthcare, protests of student fees, parking problems, and much more. There are also membership files concerning grievances on behalf of individuals, member applications, and bargaining surveys; these are restricted as there are confidentiality issues with each type of document.
There is also a selection of memorabilia that includes buttons, bumper stickers, t-shirts, posters, and photographs. Almostall of the photos came to the archives without labels or dates; therefore they are identified as clearly as a survey of the pictures would allow. The photos are bundled according to the way they arrived at the archives; the archivist placed any loose photos in clear protective sleeves.
Correspondence in each of the series is arranged according to the way the letters, e-mails, and memos were submitted to the archives: items that arrived in labeled folders were rehoused in acid-free folders and labeled similarly or exactly as the GSEU labeled them. The archivist placed items that arrived unfoldered in acid-free folders reading Correspondence general due to time constraints on item-level processing.
Approximately three cubic feet of unfoldered material experienced water damage before coming to the archives; those papers are wrinkled and may have blurred words or staining from colored paper. Most of the items were still entirely or mainly legible. The archivist photocopied a few that sustained mold damage and disposed of the originals.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Founding Documents, 1971-1998, Undated
Series 2 - Statewide Executive Committee, 1979-2000, Undated
Series 3 - SUNY Center School Administrative Files, 1974-2000, Undated
Subseries 1 - SUNY Albany, 1983-2000
Subseries 2 - SUNY Binghamton, 1974-2000
Subseries 3 - SUNY Buffalo, 1982-1999
Subseries 4 - SUNY Stony Brook, 1981-1999
Series 4 - Financial Papers, 1982-2000, Undated
Series 5 - Publications, 1982-2000, Undated
Series 6 - Subject Files, 1969-2001, Undated
Series 7 - Photos and Memorabilia, 1999-2000, Undated
Series 8 - Member Information: Applications, Grievances, Surveys, 1983-1999, Undated [RESTRICTED]
All series and subseries are arranged alphabetically with the exception of Series 7, which is arranged by format.
Labor; Education; Graduate teaching assistants; Student unions; New York (State); Albany (N.Y.); Binghamton (N.Y.); Buffalo (N.Y.); Stony Brook (N.Y.); Correspondence; Mailing Lists; Newsletters; Administrative records; Members; Minutes; Publications; Financial Records; Photographs; Memorabilia; Communications Workers of America--Education Division; Graduate Student Union(GSEU); Communications Workers of America; State University of New York; State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Binghamton; State University of New York at Buffalo; State University of New York at Stony Brook
- Founding Documents, 1971-1998; Undated; 1; 0.6 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains early drafts of the GSEU constitution and by-laws as well as some early correspondence with attorneys who provided advice on proper structuring of the group and wording of their official documents. There are also affiliation agreements between the GSEU and New York State, an agreement between the GSEU and CWA, histories of the GSEU, and some basic union fact sheets.
  - Affiliation Agreement Between GSEU and CWA, Undated (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 1)
  - Affiliation Agreement Drafts and Letters, 1975; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 2)
  - Agreement Between State of New York and GSEU, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 3)
  - Agreement Between State of New York and GSEU, 1995-1999 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 4)
  - By-Laws/ Articles  Drafts, ca. 1982 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 5)
  - By-Laws of the GSEU, 1993-1998; Undated (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 6)
  - Constitution - Advice from Attorneys Lipsitz, Green, etc., 1983 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 7)
  - Constitution  Drafts, 1982-1983 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 8)
  - Constitution of the GSEU, 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence & Pertinent Legal Documents Between GSEU, PERB, & NYS United Teachers, 1975-1976 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 10)
  - CWA Affiliation: Ballots and Voting Breakdowns, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 11)
  - Early Papers of George Kobas, Treasurer, 1970-1979 (Box 1 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 12)
  - Early Reports: GSEU and United Graduate Students, 1974; Undated (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 1)
  - Emergency ProposalsBinghamton, 1984 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 2)
  - English Department, BuffaloBreakdown of G.A. Lines, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 3)
  - French Department, BuffaloPrecursors to Organizing, 1971-1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 4)
  - Graduate Student Employees Union: An Organizing Guide, 1980-1985 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 5)
  - Guidelines for Evaluations of Graduate Programs & Student Assistantships, 1972-1976 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 6)
  - Guidelines for Organizational Activities and Campaigns, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 7)
  - History of the Formation of the GSEU, 1992-1994; Undated (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 8)
  - Memorandum of Understanding Between State of New York and GSEU, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 9)
  - Model Affiliation Agreements, Undated (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 10)
  - New GSEU Agreement Questions and Answers: Office of Employee Relations, 1994 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 11)
  - NYS United Teachers and PERB: Defining a Strike, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 12)
  - Pamphlet: Action 74, 1974-1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 13)
  - Philosophy Department, BuffaloPrecursors to Organizing, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 14)
  - Press Releases: Right to Unionize & First Contract, 1992-1994 (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 15)
  - Union Fact Sheets, 1991; Undated (Box 2 (1-Founding Documents), Folder 16)
- Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files, 1979-2000; Undated; 2; 3.0 cubic ft.
  The majority of the documents in this series originated from meetings and activities conducted by the executive committee alone or in conjunction with the officers and members of the individual school branches. However, there is one folder of central school reports that preferably should have been filed in the specific series for those schools (ie. Buffalo organizing reports in the Buffalo series), but they are physically attached so that one schools report ends and the next begins on the same page. Those few documents are therefore filed together in this series. Executive committee meetings seemed to be held at various locations around the state and it was not always clear whether material originated from executive action or steering committee action; therefore there may be executive material filed in the school series and vice versa. Other papers clearly belong either to GSEU school chapters or to the statewide executive committee and are filed accordingly. This series has many folders of meeting minutes and correspondence, but is supplemented by material on how to organize/mobilize, delegate assemblies, and steward information.
  - Agreement Between the GSEU and Staff Association, 1995-1997 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Annual CWA Convention, 2004 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Authorization Drive, 1983 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Bargaining Binder Materials, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 4-8)
  - Bargaining Folder, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 9-10)
  - By-Laws Modification Ballot for April 1995 Statewide Elections (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Candidate Statements: Officer Positions, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Center School DACS Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Certification Survey, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Contract Agreements and Proposals, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Contact Lists, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Contract Mobilization & Overall Organizer Training Meeting, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Contract Arbitrators, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - Fall Planning, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - General, Undated (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Correspondence - General, 1979; 1984; 1990-1994 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 21)
  - Correspondence - General, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence - General, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 24-26)
  - Correspondence - General, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Correspondence - General, 1998 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 28)
  - Correspondence - General, 1999 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 29)
  - Correspondence - General, 2000 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 30)
  - Correspondence - Domestic Partner Benefits, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 31)
  - Correspondence - Gleason, Dunn, Walsh and OShea, Attorneys, 1999 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 32)
  - Correspondence - Kathleen Sims and Steve Early, Negotiation Differences, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 33)
  - Correspondence - Kathleen Sims and Steve Early Regarding Legal Issues, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 34)
  - Correspondence - Letters to Governor Cuomo with Copy of Cuomo Radio Chat, 1982-1983 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 35)
  - Correspondence - Local 1031 Proposals, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 36)
  - Correspondence - National Day of Action, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 37)
  - Correspondence - Other Unions, 1984; 1991-1994 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Requests to State Legislators, 1996; Undated (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Responses to Letter-Writing Campaigns, 1995-1997; 1930 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Revisions to GSEU Articles, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Staff Association & GSEU, 1997-1999 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Underrepresented Minority Fellows, 1994-1995 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - CWA Legislative Fact Sheet: Health & Education Budget Cuts, 1998-1999 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Database Reports - GAs and TAs, Department Members, etc., 1991-1992 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1991 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1992 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1993 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1994 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1995 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1996 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1998 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Delegate Assembly 1994 - GSEU 93-94 Year in Review (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Delegate Assembly Election Materials/Ballots, 1983 (Box 2 (2-Statewide Executive Committee Administrative Files), Folder 18)